<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
    <title>Firstboot Configuration</title>
    <para>The YaST firstboot utility (YaST Initial System Configuration), which
      runs after the installation is completed, lets you configure the
      before creation of the install image so that on the
      first boot after configuration, users are guided through a series of
      steps that allow for easier configuration of their desktops. YaST
      firstboot does not run by default and has to be configured to run by the
      user or the system administrator. It is useful for image deployments
      where the system in the image is completely configured. However, some
      final steps such as root password and user logins have to be created to
      personalize the system.
    </para>
    
    <para>The default workflow for the interface is as follows: </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Welcome screen </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The License Agreement</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Date &amp; Time</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Network</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Root Password</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>User Account</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hardware</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finish</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>During firstboot, two additional dialogs are shown for writing the data and running SuSEconfig which require no user interaction.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Enabling Firstboot</title>
      <para>Firstboot is disabled by default. The yast2-firstboot package is not part of any software selection and has to be installed individually. During the Installation, click Software in the Installation Settings screen, then select the yast2-firstboot package in the Rest selection list. </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Install the product on a master box, making sure that you install the firstboot package. Configure whole system including system services, hardware components,...</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create the empty file <filename>/var/lib/YaST2/reconfig_system</filename>. This file will be deleted when firstboot configuration is completed. This can be done by issuing the command: <command>touch /var/lib/YaST2/reconfig_system</command>
</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>After getting the system installed and prepared, shut it down and
	clone the hard disk to hard disk to all of the machines.</para>
      <para>When the system comes up after a shutdown and cloning, the firstboot
	configuration utility will be started and the user will be presented
	with the configuration screens.</para>

      <para>There are different ways the firstboot configuration utility can be
	used, one of them for creating installation images. The following step
	by step description shows how an image can be created after firstboot
	has been enabled.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Boot the master box using the rescue boot option.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configure network in the rescue system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Mount an NFS exported directory to /mnt.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run <command>dd if=/dev/hda of=/mnt/image.bin
	      count=4000000</command> to store the master box's hard disk image
	    onto the NFS server.</para>

        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>And to install the image you have just created:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Boot a user's machine using the rescue boot option.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configure network in the rescue system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Mount the NFS exported directory to /mnt.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run <command>dd if=/mnt/image.bin of=/dev/hda count=4000000.</command>
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove the boot media and boot the user's machine. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>After firstboot comes up, configure the date and time, root password, and user account and any other additional settings. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The Post Configuration Utility (firstboot) expects the X server to be configured. If no X server is configured, it will automatically start in text mode.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Customizing YaST Firstboot</title>
      <section>
        <title>Customizing Messages</title>
        <para>The utility has standard and translated texts in the default
	  setup. If you want to change those texts, use the firstboot
	  configuration file,<filename>/etc/sysconfig/firstboot</filename>.</para>

        <para>This file lets you change the text of the following dialogs:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Welcome screen</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>License Agreement</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Finish dialog </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>To do this, change the values of the respective variables
	  (FIRSTBOOT_WELCOME_DIR, FIRSTBOOT_WELCOME_PATTERNS, FIRSTBOOT_LICENSE_DIR, FIRSTBOOT_NOVELL_LICENSE_DIR, and
	  FIRSTBOOT_FINISH_FILE). This will give you dialogs with customized
	  text. If the references files are in plain text, they will be shown
	  as such automatically. If they contain any markup language, they will
	  be formatted as rich text.</para>

	  <para>
	  Variable FIRSTBOOT_WELCOME_DIR is path to the directory from which is the welcome message read,
	  FIRSTBOOT_WELCOME_PATTERNS is a list of patterns or filenames which contains the message.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	  The license is read from file 'license.txt' or from 'license_&lt;locale&gt;.txt'. The license texts of the Novell base product are by default installed to the directory /etc/YaST2/licenses/base/, set different value to FIRSTBOOT_NOVELL_LICENSE_DIR if they are elsewhere. Use FIRSTBOOT_LICENSE_DIR to indicate a path to directory containing vendor licence texts; it is preferred to put these license texts into another subdirectory of /etc/YaST2/licenses/.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	  To show two license texts in one dialog (typically the one from vendor and one from Novell), use 'firstboot_license_novell' step in your firstboot.xml file. This client will use the license texts specified by both FIRSTBOOT_LICENSE_DIR and FIRSTBOOT_NOVELL_LICENSE_DIR.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	  If you want to use FIRSTBOOT_FINISH_FILE, you need to update the firstboot workflow so that it calls firstboot_finish instead of inst_congratulate. The content of the given file would be shown as the final text. 
	  However the recommended way of customizing the congratulate text is using default inst_congratulate step and specifying the text (as a value for 'congratulate' section) it in the firstboot.xml control file (see control.xml examples and documentation). With such text, it is possible to provide translations to more languages, which is not possible for FIRSTBOOT_FINISH_FILE.
	  </para>

      </section>
      <section>
        <title>License Action</title>
        <para>The variable LICENSE_REFUSAL_ACTION sets the action to be
	  executed if the user does not accept the license. The following
	  options are available:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>halt: system is halted (shut down)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>continue: continue with configuration</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>abort: Abort firstboot configuration utility and continue with the boot process.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Reboot at the end</title>
        <para>It is possible to force reboot at the end of firstboot workflow. To do so, set the value of sysconfig variable FIRSTBOOT_FINISH_ACTION to "reboot".
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Release Notes</title>
        <para>Use the configuration option FIRSTBOOT_RELEASE_NOTES_PATH to show
	  release notes in the target language. The value of the option should
	  be a path to a directory with files using language dependent naming
	  (<filename>RELEASE-NOTES.{language}.rtf</filename>). For english, the
	  following file will be needed: RELEASE-NOTES.{language}.rtf.</para>

      <para>
          The original release notes for the installed product availabe in <filename>/usr/share/doc/release-notes</filename> can be used as an
          example.
      </para>

      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Customizing Workflow Components</title>

        <para>The default firstboot workflow can be controled using one single
	  file which is a subset of the control.xml file used to control the
	  complete installation. The firstboot control file consists of
	  workflow and proposal configurations and can be used to add or remove
	  configuration screens depending on the end configuration of the
	  system. The file firstboot.xml is installed with the yast2-firstboot
	  package and can be found at the following location:
	  <filename>/etc/YaST2/firstboot.xml</filename>.</para>

        <para>This file can be modified to match the post installation
	  requirements of the product in question. In addition to the default
	  and pre-installed components, custom screens can be added to enable
	  maximal flexiblity during post installation.
<!-- For more information
	  about the syntax of the control file, see the document titled
	  “Product Installation Control”.
-->
	</para>
	<para>Instead of modifying the default /etc/YaST2/firstboot.xml file,
	it is possible to put the customized one to different location and
	specify path to it by altering the value of FIRSTBOOT_CONTROL_FILE
	variable in /etc/sysconfig/firstboot.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Scripting</title>
      <para>You can add scripts to be executed at the end of the firstboot
	configuration to customize the system depending on user input or the
	environment of the machine. Scripts should be placed in
	<filename>/usr/share/firstboot/scripts</filename> or in a custom
	location that can be set using the
	<filename>/etc/sysconfig/firstboot</filename> configuration
	file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Firstboot and AutoYaST</title>
	<para>
	It is possible to configure the firstboot process as a part of
	autoinstallation, so the system can be installed with most of the
	default values set via AutoYaST profile, leaving the rest to the end
	user during the firstboot sequence.
	</para>
	<para>
	As a part of autoinstallation configuration, you need to provide
	all the changes mentioned above:
	</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Customize <filename>/etc/sysconfig/firstboot</filename>:
	    it can be done e.g. via
	    Sysconfig Editor in System section of AutoYaST configuration module.
	    </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Provide customized firstboot.xml file and point to its
	    location in FIRSTBOOT_CONTROL_FILE value of
	    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/firstboot</filename>.
	    </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enable Firstboot: do it via GUI in Misc/Firstboot section of
	    AutoYaST configuration module or manually by adding the section
	    <screen>
		<![CDATA[
<firstboot>
    <firstboot_enabled config:type="boolean">true</firstboot_enabled>
</firstboot>
]]>
	    </screen>
	    to your AutoYaST profile.
	    </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
